Guide to the Technology and Society Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- Yale Technology Project records, Accession 1985-A-066
  - New York Trust Study, Series XIII
    The study of the New York Trust Company, beginning in 1955 and continuing through 1954, was a consulting program designed to help the bank assess its personnel policies and improve the morale and qualifications of its employees, particularly those at the upper levels. The heart of the study was the series of interviews with most of the executive officers and many of the senior clerks in all of the divisions of the bank. These formed the basis of the reports to the bank and the counseling on the bank's educational program.
    On the nature of the consulting program, see the statement in file 02 and the correspondence, especially the first four items, in file 03. Among the documents, the comprehensive organizational chart (file 07, item 1) is an essential reference.
    The interviews were conducted by Charles R. Walker, Arthur N. Turner and Robert N. Guest. They all followed a similar pattern (see file 10), covering the employee's work history, job duties; comments on personnel policies and practices and suggestions for the educational and training program. The interviews are quite comprehensive and are rich in accounts of incidents and reflections about the bank. The interview extracts (files 12-28) constitute sentence or paragraph length comments on the various topics covered.
    The training and educational program was established and run by the bank itself, with advice from the researcher-consultants. Thus files 29-52 contain mostly company documents. The program was run by a Committee on Education formed in 1953 with senior officers as members. Some of the correspondence (file 03) concerns the training. The Committee supervised the courses on banking given to the officers and also considered the bank's policies on other personnel matters, including turnover, transfers and promotion. Except for the sketch in file 42, all of the reports written by the consultants (files 35-42) were written for the Committee on Education. The Harvard Business School case studies (files 43-44) were considered as models or teaching materials for the bank's classes.
    - New York Trust Study (Box 87, Box 88, Box 86, Folder 1-44)
      - Duplicates (Box 88, Folder 1-44)
  - AVCO Study, Series XIV
    The Avco Study was a consulting project that began in 1953 and ended in 1957. The Lyconing division's plant in Stratford, Connecticut was a new aircraft engine factory that was having problems related to its rapid growth, its fluctuating business and its management morale. Charles R. Walker and Associates were hired to make a report on supervisory morale (see file 62) and then served as consultants advising on a wide range of problems. The consultants, mainly Frank J. Jasinski and Robert H. Guest but also Arthur N. Turner and Charles R. Walker, became deeply involved in the management process, sometimes acting as managers as well as advisors. Thus the study was not a simple objective survey, but a distillation of the company's experiences over a period of several years.
    This complex consulting role is reflected in the material in the files, which could be thoroughly described in the tables of contents only at the cost of excessive time and expense. The research material can only be thoroughly understood by actually going through it. The tables of contents of the important files simply list and identify the items, without attempting a descriptive summary of them. While the most important dimension of the study was chronological (changes over time) rather than organizational (conflicts between different levels of management) the files have been arranged so as to sort out the complex organization of the Division.
    A separate plant, at Williamsport, Pennsylvania, within the Lycoming Division is treated in two files (58, 70). Two major manufacturing units at the Stratford plant were studied: the Jet operation, and the Reciprocating Engine Operation, commonly called the Wright operation. Other units, notably the Gas Turbine project, affected Jet and Wright, but they were not studied directly. A great deal of attention given to the general management of the plant, that is, the chief executives and the middle management officials in the service departments (such as industrial relations, quality control and engineering). The files have been organized along these lines.
    Organizational boundaries were not always clear in the consulting program or in the operations of the plant. In 1953 and 1954 Wright and Jet were a study in contrast, but thereafter the consultants usually dealt with the Division as a whole or with particular problems in many areas of the plant. In addition, Lycoming had a very fluid management corps. Turnover was high and transfers were frequent. Changes in personnel, rank and duties are not always recorded clearly. A list of executives and their changing assignments is attached to this guide as an aid in reducing the confusion.
    As the list of Reports (files 61-72) suggests, the Avco study was both wide-ranging and compact. Many topics were covered and little of the material in the files is unimportant. Among the company documents, the organizational charts, the personnel material and the management development program are especially important (files 06-08). The union grievance described in file 15 was a major incident. The researchers' notes on management meetings (files 46-50) are probably more useful than the official minutes (files 16-25).
    Of course, the heart of the study is contained in the management interviews and observations. The interviews with the general foremen and foremen were not in-depth and were infrequent after 1954, but the talks with higher officials were frequent and very comprehensive. The observations include a variety of material: reports on specific incidents and the general events of the day; brief conversations with a series of people (rather than individual interviews); and some interviews with some persons who did not fit - as far as could be determined - into the regular organizational framework.
    Of the Departmental Surveys, the study of Department 3-D is especially important (file 52). At the request of management, one foreman in 3-D was closely observed for an entire working day in order to record and analyze all his activities (file 54). The production survey and personnel statistics were part of an effort in 1955-1956 to analyze the plant's problems with low production (files 59-60).
    All of the reports are significant, but the Report on Supervision is comprehensive, providing the context for the work that followed.
    - AVCO Study (Box 91, Box 92, Box 93, Box 90, Box 89, Folder 1-72)
      - Duplicates (Box 93–94)
  - Research Files, Series XV
    - Research Files (Box 96, Box 100, Box 99, Box 98, Box 95, Folder 1-48, Box 97)
  - Research Pamphlets, Series XVI
    - Research Pamphlets (Box 101, Folder 1-67, Box 102)
  - Research Periodicals and Government Publications, Series XVII
    - Research Periodicals (Box 103, Folder 1-40)
    - Government Publications (Box 104, Folder 1-14)
    - Duplicates (Box 105–108)